下面几节我们稍微变点讨论方向
In the next three segments we will change
gears a little bit and talk about the
看看PRG的定义
这个定义是理解PRG的好方法
definition of a PRG. This definition is a
really good way to think of a PRG. And we
我们可以看到这个定义的许多应用
will see many applications for this
definition. So consider a PRG with
令PRG有密钥空间K，即N位字符串的集合
我们的目标是定义
keyspace K that ouputs N bit strings. Our
goal is to define, what does it mean for
发生器输出与随机序列无法区分的意义
the output of the generator to be
indistinguishable from random? In other
换句话说，我们要定义一个分布
从密钥空间里选择密钥时的分布
words, we're gonna define a distribution
that basically is defined by choosing a
记得带R的箭头意思是
random key in the keyspace. Remember that
a arrow with R above it means choosing
从集合K里均匀地随机选取
然后发生器的输出
uniformly from the set script K. And then
we output, basically, the output of the
我们说这就是个分布
generator. And what we'd like to say. Is
that this distribution. This distribution
这个伪随机字符串的分布
与真正的均匀分别没有分别
of pseudo random strings is
indistinguishable from a truly uniform
换句话说，如果我们选择一个
均匀随机分布的N位0,1字符串
distribution. In other words, if we just
choose a truly uniform string in 01 to the
输出该字符串，我们说这两个分布
N and simply output this string, we'd like
to say that these two distributions are
是不能互相区分的，大家想想
indistinguishable from one another. Now if
you think about it, this sounds really
这有点意外的，因为如果我们
画个圈表示所有N位0,1字符串
surprising because if we draw a circle
here of all possible strings in 01 to the
那么均匀分布会以同等概率
输出这些字符串
N, then the uniform distribution basically
can output any of these strings with equal
这是均匀分布的定义
probability. That's the definition of the
uniform distribution. However a
不过这个发生器G生成的伪随机分布
pseudo-random distribution generated by
this generator G. Because the seed space
因为种子空间太小，可能输出结果的集合
是很小很小的
is so small, the set of possible outputs
is really, really small, it's tiny inside
是N位0,1字符串集合中一个很小的子集
这是发生器所能产生的一切
of, 01 to the N. And this is really all
that the generator can output. And yet,
我们说，有个攻击者在观测发生器的输出
what we're arguing is that an adversary
who looks at the output of the generator
也就是这个小集合里的元素，它与
均匀分布的输出无法区分
in this tiny set can't distinguish it from
the output of the uniform distribution
我想这个性质就是我们想要的
over the entire set. I think that's the
property that we're actually shooting for.
为了理解如何定义这个与真随机
不可区分的概念
So to understand how to define this
concept of indistinguishability from
我们需要引入统计测试的概念
random, we need the concept of a
statistical test. So, let me define what a
我来定义N位0,1字符串的统计测试
我用字母A来表示这些统计测试
statistical test on 01 to the N is. I'm
gonna define these statistical tests by
统计测试是一个算法
the letter A. And the statistical test is
basically an algorithm that takes its
以N位字符串为输入，输出0或1
inputs and N bit string, and simply
outputs zero or one. Now I'll tell you
输出0，我们把它想象成统计测试说
that zero, we're gonna think of it as
though the statistical test said, the
输入的字符串不是随机的
1的话我们可以想象成
input you gave me is not random. And one,
we're going to think of it as saying that
测试结果认为输入字符串是随机的
好，统计测试所做的
the input you gave me actually is random.
Okay, so all this statistical test does is
就是取输入x，即给定的n位字符串
it basically takes the input x that was
given to it, the n bit string that was
然后判断它是否看起来像是随机的
given to it, and decides whether it looks
random or it doesn't look random. Let's
我们看几个例子，第一个例子运用一个事实
look at a couple of examples. So the first
example basically will use the fact that
那就是，对于一个随机字符串
0的个数和1的个数大体相等
for a random string, the number of zeros
is roughly equal to the number of ones in
换句话说，统计测试输出1
that string. In other words, the
statistical test is going to say one. If
当且仅当字符串X里0的个数减去1的个数
and only if basically the number of zeros
in the given string X minus the number of
这些数不会差太多，换句话说
1's in the given string X. These numbers
are not too far apart. In other words, the
0个数和1个数的差别
difference between the number of 0's and
the number of 1's. Let's just say is less
比如说小于n的10倍平方根
好，如果差别小于n的10倍平方根
than ten times square root of n. Okay. If
the difference is less than ten times, the
统计测试就会说字符串X像是随机的
statistical test will say hey the
string X looks random. If the
如果比n的10倍平方根大得多
difference happens to be much bigger than
ten times square root of n, that starts to
测试就会怀疑，觉得给的字符串
look suspicious and the test,
hey the string you gave me does not
不像是随机的。这是一个统计测试
我们再看一个例子
look random. A statistical test. Let's
look at another similar example. We'll say
统计测试说1，当且仅当字符串X中
here, the statistical test will say one.
If and only if say the number of times
出现连续两个0的次数
that we have two consecutive zeros. Inside
of X. But let's think about this for a
想一想，数一数，n位字符串中
second. This basically again counts. In
this string of, n bits. It counts a number
数一数00出现的个数，连续两个0
of times that we see the pattern zero,
zero. Two consecutive zeros. Well for a
对于一个随机字符串，我们期望
00的概率应该是四分之一
random string. We will expect to see 0,0
as probability one fourth. And there for
对于一个随机字符串，我们期望
有大约N/4个00，对，N/4
in a random string. We'll expect about N
over four 0,0's. Yeah, N over four blocks
那么这个统计测试会这么做
a 0,0. And so, what the statistical test
will do is it will say, well, if the
如果00的个数大约是N/4，换句话说，
number of zero zeros is roughly N over
four. In other words, the difference
00的个数与N/4的差别小于
n的10倍平方根
between the number and N over four,
is, say, less than ten square root of n,
那我们就可说X像是随机的
如果这个差别远远大于N/4
then we will say that X looks random. And
if the gap is much bigger than N over
那我们说字符串X不像是随机的
four, we'll say, hey, this string doesn't
really look random. And then the
(差别gap应为远远大于n的10倍平方根)
然后统计测试就会输出0，对吧？
那么就是这两个统计测试的例子
statistical test will output zero, okay?
So here are two examples of statistical
对于随机字符串，它们会以很大的概率
tests that basically, for random strings,
they will output one with very high
输出1.对看起来不怎么随机的字符串
probability. But for strings that, you
know, don't look random, for example,
比如全是0的字符串
think of the all zero string. So the all
zero string, neither one of these tests
没有测试会输出1，事实上
全是0的字符串看起来不随机
will output, one. And in fact, the all
zero string does not look random. Let's
我们再看一个统计测试的例子
look at one more example of the
statistical test just to kinda show you
来为大家展示统计测试可以想怎么做
the, basically statistical test can pretty
much do whatever they want. So here's the
看第三个例子。我们说统计测试输出1
third example. Let's say that statistical
test output one if an only if I say the
当且仅当最大的块，我们叫0的最大游程
biggest blocks what we'll call this the
Maximum Run of zero inside of the string
在字符串x中最长的连续的0
x, this is basically the longest sequence
of zero inside of the string x. In a
在随机字符串里，我们期望
0的最长游程大约是
random string you expect the longest
sequence of zeros to be roughly of length
log N。我们说如果0的最长游程
log N. So we'll say if the longest
sequence of zero happens to be less than
(2为底数)
小于10log N，那么测试结果认为X是随机的
ten times log N. Then this test will say
that X was random. But if, all of a
但如果有0的游程远远大于10log N
sudden, we see a run of zeros that, say,
is much bigger than ten log N, then the
那么统计测试会说这个字符串不随机
statistical test will say, the string is
not random, okay? So this is another crazy
对吧？这又是个统计测试的疯狂例子
顺便说下，注意到给定测试
thing that the statistical test will do.
By the way, you notice that if you give
全是1的字符串1111..
this test, the all one string. So one,
one, one, one, one. This test will also
这个测试也会输出1.换句话说这个测试
认为全是1的字符串也是随机的
output one. In other words this test will
think that the all one string is random.
即使它不是，即使全1字符串不随机
Even though it's not. Yeah, even though
one string is not particularly random.
好的，那么统计测试不一定总是对的
Okay, so statistical tests don't have to
get things right. They can do whatever
它们可以想怎么来就怎么来
它们可以测试，判断、输出是否随机
they like. They can test, they can decide
to output random or not. You know, zero or
也就是0或1，类似地还有许多其他统计测试
one, however they like. And similarly,
there are many, many, many, many other
谁都可以造几百个统计测试出来
statistical tests. There are literally
hundreds of statistical tests that one can
告诉大家在以前
think of. And I can tell you that in the
old days, basically, the way you would
定义某物看起来随机的方法
你会说，有好多统计测试
define that something looks random. As
you would say, hey, here's a battery of
所有的方法都说这个字符串是随机的
statistical tests. And all of them said
that this string looks random. Therefore,
那么我们就是这个发生器生成的字符串
是随机的，是个好发生器
we say that this generator that generated
the string is good generator. In other
换句话说，这个定义使用了
一个固定的统计测试的集合
words, this definition, then, uses a fixed
set of statistical tests, is actually not
因此不是安全性的良好定义
对于更一般的密码学而言
a good definition for security, but more
generally, for crytpo. But before we talk
但在我们讨论安全性定义前
我们还需讨论
about actually defining security, the next
thing we talk about is how do we evaluate
如何评估一个统计测试
为此，我们定义优势的概念
whether a statistical test is good or not?
So to do that, we define the concept of
让我定义优势的意思
advantage. And so let me define the
advantage. So here we have a generator
我们有一个生成N位字符串的发生器
我们有N位字符串的统计测试
that outputs N bit strings. And we have a
statistical tests on N bit strings. And we
我们定义这个发生器的优势
记为优势子PRG
define the advantage of this generator,
as denoted by advantage sub PRG,
统计测试A相对于发生器g的优势
the advantage of the statistical test A
relative to the generator g. I'll define
我如下定义优势，定义为两个量的差
it as follows, basically the difference
between two quantities. The first quantity
第一个量是统计测试输出1的可能性
is basically, we ask how likely is this
statistical test to output one. When we
当我们给它一个伪随机字符串
就像这里k是均匀选取的
give it a pseudo random string just like
here K is chosen uniformly from the C
我们关注统计测试输出1的可能性
space we ask how likely is the statistical
test to output one when we give it a
当输入是由发生器生成的伪随机输出
pseudo random output generated by the
generator verses now we ask how likely is
同时我们还要看输入是真随机字符串时
the statistical test to output one when we
give it a truly random string. So here are
那么这里是真随机的n位01字符串
is truly random in zero random one to the
n. Okay, and yeah. We look at the
好的，我们看两个量的差
difference between these two quantities.
Now you realize because these are
因为是概率的差，所以差别应该在
differences of probabilities this
advantage is always going to lie in the
区间[0,1]里。我们来想想
interval zero, one. So let's think a
little bit about what this advantage
这个优势的意思。首先，
如果优势接近于1
actually means. So first of all if the
advantage happens to be close to one. Well
什么意思？当我们输入伪随机数时
what does that mean? That means that
somehow, the statistical test A behaves
和输入真随机数时，统计测试A
表现得完全不同
differently when we gave it pseudo-random
inputs, when we gave it the output of the
对吧？它表现地不一样
generator, for when we gave it truly
random inputs, right? It somehow behaved
一种情况下，它以一定概率输出1
differently. In one case, it output one
with a certain probability. And in the
另一情况下，它以别的概率输出1
other case, it output one with a very
different probability, okay? So somehow,
对吧？它就能表现不同。这样一来
it was able to behave differently. And
what they really means is that the
这个统计测试就能将这个发生器的输出
statistical test could basically
distinguish the output of the generator
和真随机区分开来。好的，某种意义上
我们说这个统计测试
from random. Okay, so in some sense we'll
say that this statistical test broke the
破解了发生器G，因为可以区分
输出序列和真随机序列
generator G because it was able to
distinguish the output from random.
但是如果这个优势跟0很近
什么意思？
However if the advantage is close to zero
Well what does that mean? That means that
这意味着统计测试在两种情况下
表现地基本一致
basically the statistical tests behaves
pretty much the same on pseudo random
对真随机的输入，我们基本上可以说
inputs. As it does on truly random inputs.
And basically there we would say that A
测试A无法区分发生器输出和真随机
could not distinguish the generator from
random. Okay, so this sum gives you a
这个可以给大家一点直观感受
感受优势这一重要概念
little bit of intuition about why this
concept of advantage is important. It
它告诉我们测试A能否破解发生器
basically tells us whether A was able to
break the generator, namely distinguish it
即区分随机性，要不就不能破解之
那么我们再看一个傻傻的例子
from random, or not able to break it. So
let's look, first of all, at a very silly
假设我们有一个统计测试A
它不管输入是什么
example. Suppose we have a statistical
test A that simply ignores its inputs and
总是输出0。好，总是输出0
大家觉得相对于任一发生器G
always outputs zero. Okay. Always output
zero. What do you think of the advantage
所拥有的优势是多少？
of this statistical test relative to a
generator G? So, I hope everybody
我希望大家都能认为优势是0
我解释一下为什么
say the advantage is zero, let
me just explain, why that's the case,
如果在测试中，总是输出0
well, if the statistical test,
always outputs, zero, that
这意味着，输入伪随机序列时，
它绝不输出1，所以以概率0输出1
means, pseudo random inputs, it will never
output one, so, the probability that
类似地，输入真随机序列时
outputs one, is zero. Similarly, when we
give a truly random input, it still will
它依然不会输出1，其概率还是0
never output one, and, so, the probability
that outputs one, is zero,
所以0减0等于0，故优势为0
and, so, zero minus zero is zero, so, its
advantage is zero, so, basically, and, a
这个测试根本不看输入
显然根本无法区分
statistical test that ignores its, its
input, does not able to distinguish, truly
真随机和伪随机，好
random inputs, from, a pseudo random
input, obviously. Okay, now let's look at
下个例子更有趣点。假设我们的发生器G
a more interesting example. So suppose we
have a generator G that satisfies a funny
满足一个有趣的性质：对三分之二的密钥
property. It so happens that for
two-thirds of the keys, the first bit
发生器输出的第一位是1，怎么样？
of the output of the generator happens to
be one, okay? So if I choose a random key
所以如果我随机选取一个密钥
发生器以2/3的概率，第一位输出为1
with probability two-thirds, the generator
will output one as its first bit, okay? So
好吧？这就是这个发生器的性质
that's the property of the generator that
we're looking at. Now, let's look at the
我们来看下面这个统计测试
这个测试是这样的
following statistical test. The
statistical test basically says, if the
如果字符串最高位是1，就输出1
most signifigant bit of the string you
gave me is one, I'm gonna say one, meaning
任何这是随机的；如果输入的最高位不是1
I think it's random. If the most signigant
bit of the stream you gave me is not one,
是0，那就输出0
给大家的问题是
zero, I'm gonna say zero. Okay
so now my question to you is what is the
这个统计测试对发生器G的优势是多少？
advantage of this statistical test on the
generator G? Okay, so remember I just
好，我记得优势的定义写在这了
大家可以想一想
wrote down the definition here again. And
I'll let you think about this for a
我来解释一下。假设我们对这个统计测试
输入伪随机序列
second. So let me explain. Suppose we give
the statistical tests pseudo random
根据G的定义，我们知道以2/3的概率
inputs. By definition of G, we know that
with probability two-thirds, the first
输入的第一位是1。但如果是以1开头
bits in the inputs will start with the bit
one. But if it starts with a bit one, then
测试结果会是1，换句话说
the statistical test will output one. In
other words, the probability that this
统计测试输出1的概率严格地为2/3
我们再看真随机的情况
statistical test outputs one is exactly
two-thirds. Now let's look at the case of
如果我给一个真随机的字符串
a random string. If I give you a random
string, how likely is it that the most
最高位是1的概率是多少？
对于真正随机的字符串
signifigant bits of the random string is
one? Well, for a random string, that
最高位是1约占一半，这时
统计测试会输出1
happens exactly half the time, and so in
this case the statistical test will output
也就是以1/2的概率，所以总的
优势为1/6
one, with probability one-half. And so the
overall advantage is one-sixth, and
1/6不是一个可忽略的量了
是个相当大的数了
one-sixth is actually a non-negligible
number, that's actually a fairly large
这意味着这个发生器可以区分输出了
number, which basically means that this a
was able to distinguish the output. We'll
我们说A以优势1/6破解了发生器G
say that A breaks the generator G with
advantage 1/6. Okay, which basically
这说明这个发生器不怎么好
被破解了，好
means that this generator is no good, is
broken. Okay, so now that we understand
现在我们理解了统计测试是什么了
现在可以进一步去定义
what statistical tests are, we can go
ahead and define, what is a secure
什么是安全的伪随机数发生器
我们说发生器G是安全的
pseudo-random generator. So, basically, we
say that, as generator G is secure, if
如果不存在有效的统计测试
可以区分发生器G的输出
essentially no efficient, statistical
tests can distinguish its output from
和真随机序列。更精确地
我们说，对所有有效的统计测试
random. More precisely, what we'll say is
that, basically for all efficient
如果我看其优势
statistical tests, a... Statistical tests,
a... It so happens that if I look at the
统计测试E对发生器G的优势
advantage. Of the statistical test E
relative to G. This advantage basically is
基本上这个优势是可忽略的
换句话说，它很接近于0
negligible. So, in other words,
it's very close to zero, and as a result,
这样统计测试不能区分发生器输出
和真随机序列
this, statistical test was not able to
distinguish the output from random, and
这点对所有的统计测试都成立
that has to be true for all statistical
tests. So, this is a very, very pretty and
所以这个定义非常优雅
一个生成器是安全的
elegant definition, that says that a
generator is secure, not only if a
不仅特定的统计测试认为它的输出
是随机的，事实上对所有
particular battery of statistical tests
says that the output looks random, but, in
有效的统计测试，都认为输出是随机的
fact, all efficient statistical tests will
say the output looks random. Okay? One
好吧？我需要指出一点
限制为有效的统计测试是必须的
thing I'd like to point out is, that the
restriction to efficient statistical tests
如果我们不说是有效的
而是看所有可能的统计测试的话
is actually necessary. If we ask that all
statistical tests, regardless of whether
所有统计测试都无法区分输出和真随机
they're efficient or not, not be able to
distinguish the output from random. Then
事实上，这无法被满足
换句话说，如果我们
in fact, that can not be satisfied. So in
other words if we took out the
去掉测试是有效的这一要求
这个定义将无法被满足
requirements that the test be efficient.
Then this definition would be
这点留给大家想一想
unsatisfiable. And I'll leave this as a
simple puzzle for you to think about. But
(提示：有效是说，测试算法总在有限步内
终止并返回结果)
基本上在定义里加上只有有效测试
basically the fact is that restricting
this definition into only efficient
这一限制，就是为了让定义是可满足的
statistical tests is actually necessary
for this to be satisfiable. So now that we
有了定义，下一个问题是
我们能不能构建这么一个发生器
have a definition, the next question is
can we actually construct a generator and
然后证明它是个安全的PRG呢？
换句话说，证明没有一个有效测试
then prove that it is in fact a secure
PRG. In other words, prove that no
可以区分发生器的输出和真随机
efficient statistical test can distinguish
its output from random. And it turns out
事实上，答案是我们不能
就是不知道
that the answer is we actually can't. In
fact, it's not known. If there are any
如果有任何极有可能是安全的PRG
我说，简单的原因在于
probably secure PRG's. Then I will just
say very briefly the reason is that if you
如果你能证明一个特定的发生器是安全的
那就意味着
could prove that a particular generator is
secure that would actually imply that P
P不等于NP，我还不想纠结在这
is not equal to NP. And I don't want to
dwell on this. Because I don't want to
因为可能大家有些不知道P和NP
那我就告诉大家如果P=NP
assume that you guys know what P and NP
are. But I'll tell you as a simple fact
会发生什么。那样的话
很容易证明不存在安全的PRG
that in fact in P is equal to NP. Then
it's very easy to show that there are no
所以如果你能给我证明一个PRG是安全的
secure PRGs. And so if you could prove to
me that a particular PRG is secure, that
那也就意味着P不等于NP
would imply that P is not equal to
NP. Again, I will leave this to
这点也留给大家想想
you as a simple puzzle to think about.
But, even though we can't actually
(提示：逆否命题)
尽管我们不能严格地证明某个PRG
是安全的，我们还是有
rigorously prove that a particular PRG is
secure, we still have lots and lots and
大量的PRG候选方案，之前看过一些
lots of heuristic candidates, and we even
saw some of those in the previous
好，现在我们理解了什么是安全PRG
segments. Okay now that we understand what
is a secure PRG. I want to talk a little
我想谈一下这个定义的
一些应用和影响
bit about some applications and
implications of this definition. And so
第一个，事实上安全的PRG
the first thing I want to show you is that
in fact a secure PRG is necessarily
是不可预测的，前面几节
我们讨论了发生器不可预测的意思
unpredictable. In a previous segment, we
talked about what it means for a generator
我们说，这个的意思是
to be unpredictable. And we said that,
basically, what that means is that, given
给定发生器输出的前缀
是不可能预测出输出的下一位是什么
a prefix of the output generator, it's
impossible to predict the next bit of the
好，所以我们想展示一个发生器是否安全
output. Okay, so we'd like to show that if
a generator is secure, then necessarily,
必须意味着它是不可预测的
所以我们唯一的方法是
it means it's unpredictable. And so the
only way we're gonna do that is using the
使用逆否命题，也就是，我们说
如果你给出一个可预测的发生器
contrapositive. That is, we're gonna say
that if you give me a generator that is
那么这就意味着它是不安全的
predictable, then necessarily, it's
insecure. In other words, necessarily, I
换句话说，我能把它从真随机中区分出来
这是个很简单的事实
can distinguish it from random. And so
let's see, this is actually a very simple
那我们看看怎么用这个事实
假设你给出了一个预测算法
fact. And so let's see how we would do
that. So suppose you give me a predictor.
换句话说，假设你有一个有效算法
In other words, suppose you give me an
efficient algorithm, such that, in fact,
如果我把发生器的输出作为其输入
if I give this algorithm the output of the
generator, but I give it only the first
只给前I位，该算法可以预测输出的下一位
I-bits of the outputs. It's able to
predict the next bit of the output. In
换句话说，给定前I位
可以预测第I+1位
other words given the first I-bit it's
able to predict the I plus first bit. And
以特定的概率。比如说我们取随机密钥k
it does that with a certain probability.
So let's say if we choose a random k. From
从密钥空间中。然后，预测机可以
the keyspace. Then, clearly, a done
predictor would be able to predict the
以1/2概率预测下一位，简单猜测
next bit with probability one-half, simply
just guess the bits. You'll be right with
也可以做到1/2概率成功预测
但是这个算法A可以预测下一位
probability one-half. However, this
algorithm A is able to predict the next
以1/2加Epsilon的概率，是这样界定的
bit with probability half with epsilon. So
it's bound to the way. From a half. And,
事实上，我们要求这对某些不可忽略的
Epsilon成立，例如
in fact, we require that this by true for
some non negligible epsilon. So, for
Epsilon为千分之一，这就是个
很危险的预测算法了
example, epsilon =1/1000 would already be a
dangerous predictor, because it can
因为它可以预测下一位，给定前缀
以一个不可忽略的优势
predict the next bits, given a prefix,
with non negligible advantage. Okay, so
好，设想我们有一个算法
我们可以使用这个算法破解发生器
suppose we have such an algorithm. Let's
see that we can use this algorithm to
换句话说，可以区分这个发生器的输出
break our generator. In other words to
show that a generator is distinguishable
和真随机，这个发生器是不安全的
所以我们将定义一个统计测试
from random and therefore, is insecure. So
what we'll do is we'll define a
那么我们如下定义统计测试B
statistical test. So, let's define the
statistical test B as follows. Basically,
给定字符串x，B在前I位上运行算法A
B, given a string, x, what it will do, is
it will simply run algorithm A on the
然后统计测试简单地问一下
first I-bit of the string x that it was
given. And, statistical test b is simply
算法A是否成功地预测了第I+1位？
gonna ask, was a successful in predicting
the I-plus first bit of the string? If it
如果成功了，返回1
如果不成功，返回0
was successful, then it's gonna output
one. And if it wasn't successful, then
好，这就是我们的统计测试
我们把它放在一个盒子里
it's gonna output zero. Okay. This our
statistical task. Let's put it in a box.
那么我们可以随时使用他
对任意N位字符串
So we can take it wherever we like. And we
can run the statistical test on any N bit
我们都可以运行这个统计测试
现在，我们看会发生什么
string that's given to us as inputs. So
now, let's look at what happens. Suppose
假设我们给这个统计测试输入
真随机的字符串，也就是R
we give the statistical test, a truly
random string. So a truly random string R.
我们问，统计测试输出1的概率是多少？
And we ask, what is the probability that
the statistical test outputs one? Well,
因为是真随机字符串，I+1位
与前面I位是完全独立的
for a truly random string, the I+1
bit is totally independent of the first
所以算法A的输出
I-bits. So whatever this algorithm is
gonna output is completely independent of
也与字符串R的第I+1位完全独立
所以不管A输出什么
what's, I+1 bit of the string R is.
And so whatever A outputs the probability
输出与第I+1位独立
is going to be equal to some random
bit X I+1. Random independent bit X I+1, that
概率为1/2。换句话说，算法A
probability is exactly 1/2. In other
words, algorithm a simply has no
不提供第I+1位的任何信息
information about what the bit X I+1
is, and so necessarily, the probability is
故成功预测I+1位的概率为1/2
另一方面，我们看一下
able to predict X I+1 is exactly
one half. On the other hand, let's look at
当我们给统计测试一段伪随机序列时
what happens when we give our statistical
tests a pseudo-random sequence, okay. So
我们对发生器的输出进行统计测试B
now we're going to run the statistical
test on the output of the generator, and
我们问，测试输出1的可能性是多大？
根据算法A的定义
we ask how likely is it to output one.
Well, by definition of A, we know that
当我们给定发生器输出的前I位时
when we give it the first I bits of the
output of the generator, it's able to
算法A成功预测下一位的概率是1/2
加上Epsilon
predict the next bit with probability
1/2 + epislon. So in this case our
这时我们的统计测试B会
以大于1/2+Epsilon的概率输出1
statistical test B will output one with
probability greater than 1/2 + epsilon
这个的意思是，如果我们看
And basically what this means,
is if we look at the advantage of our
我们统计测试对发生器G的优势
也就是这两个量之间的差距
statistical tests over the generator G
it's basically, the difference between
两者有差别
this quantity and that quantity. There's a
difference between the two. You can see
容易看出，它比Epsilon大
这意味着，如果算法A
that it's clearly greater than an epsilon.
So what this means is that if algorithm A
可以以优势Epsilon预测下一位
is able to predict the next bits with
advantage epsilon, then algorithm B is
那么测试算法B可以以优势Epsilon
区分出发生器的输出序列，对吧？
able to distinguish the output of the
generator with advantage epsilon. Okay? So
如果A是个好的预测算法，B是个
好的统计测试，可以破解发生器
if A is a good predictor, B is a good
statistical test that break the generator.
我们说这个逆否命题是说
如果发生器G安全
And as we said, the counter-positive of
that is that if G is a secure generator,
没有任何好的统计测试
也就没有任何好的预测算法
then there are no good statistical tests.
And as a result, there are no predictors.
对吧？这也就意味着
这个发生器是不可预测的
Okay? Which means that the generator is,
as we said, unpredictable. Okay, so, so
好，目前我们知道，如果发生器是安全的
far, what we've seen is that if the
generator is secure, necessarily, it's
给定前I位，也不可能预测第I+1位
impossible to predict the I+1 bit,
given first I bits.
1982年姚期智给出了一个优雅重要的定理
Now there's a very elegant and remarkable
theorem Yao back in 1982. They
(1982年论文Theory and application
of trapdoor functions，用熵的观点证明)
事实上，逆命题也成立，换句话说
chose it, in fact the converse is also
true. In other words, if I give you a
如果我给大家的发生器是不可预测的
不可由前I位预测第I+1位
generator that's unpredictable, so you
cannot predict the I+1 bits from the
对任意I都成立，那么这个发生器
事实上就是安全的
first I bits, and that's true for all I.
That generator, in fact, is secure. Okay,
好，我把这个定理说的更清楚点
so let me state the theorem a little bit
more precicely. So here we have our
这里我们的发生器输出n位字符串
这个定理告诉我们
generator that outputs n bit outputs. The
theorem says the following, basically for
对任何位置I，不可能根据前I位
预测输出的第I+1位
all bit positions, it's impossible to
predict I+1 bit of the output
这对任何I都成立，换句话说
given the first I bit. And that's true for
all I. In other words, again, the
这个发生器对所有位置都不可预测
那么事实上这意味着
generator is unpredictable for all bit
positions. Then, that, in fact, implies
这个PRG就是安全的
我还想用应用重新组织下语言
that the generator is a secure PRG.
I want paraphrase this in English,
这个结果解读为，这些下一位预测算法
and so the way to kinda interpret this
result is to say that it's basically these
这些预测算法试图预测第I+1位
next bit predictors. These predictors that
try to predict the I+1 bit given the
给定前I+1位。如果它们不能把G的输出
和真随机区分开来
first I bits. If they're not able to
distinguish G from random, then, in fact,
那么事实上，就没有统计测试可以
区分G和真随机
no statistical test is going to
distinguish G from random. So kind of next
这些下一位预测算法某种意义上
是泛指的预测算法
bit predictors are in some sense
universal, predictors, when it comes to
当它用来区分随机性时
顺带一说，这个定理不难证明
distinguishing things from random. This
theorem, by the way, it's not too
证明有一个很优雅的思路
difficult to prove, but there's a very
elegant idea behind its proof. I'm not
我不给出具体证明，我鼓励
大家自己想想
gonna do the proof here, but I encourage
you to think about this as a puzzle, try
试图自己证明之
我们看一下这个定理的影响
to kind of try to prove this theorem
yourself. Let me show you kind of one cute
我问下面这个问题
implication of this theorem. So let me ask
you the following question. Suppose I give
假设我给大家一个发生器，告诉大家
给定输出的最后一位
you a generator and I tell you that given
the last bit of the output. It's easy to
容易预测输出的第一位，对吧？
那么给最后一位
predict the first bit of the outputs,
okay? So given the last end bits, you can
你可以计算出第一位
这和可预测正好相反，对吧？
compute the first end bits. That's kind of
the opposite of predictability, right?
可预测是说给第一位，
你可以算出下一位
Predictability mean given the first
bit, you can produce the next bits. Here,
这里是给最后一位，你可以算出第一位
我给大家的问题是
given the last bits, you can produce the
first ones. And my question to you, does
这是否意味着这个发生器是可预测的？
that mean that the generator is
predictable? Can you somehow, from this
能否根据这点，为这个发生器
构造一个预测算法呢？
fact, still build a predictor for this
generator? This is kind of a simple
这是姚定理的一个简单应用
答案是可以，我解释一下
application of Yao theorem. let me explain to
you the answer is actually yes let me
如何构造这个预测算法
实际上我不用构造之
explain why how do we build this generator
well, actually we're not going to build it
我证明它存在即可
I'm going to show you that the generator
exists. Well because an over two bits
(口误generator，应为predictor)
首先，超过两字节不意味着这个发生器
first an over two bits doesn't necessarily
mean that the generator. Here let me write
我这样写，意思是g不安全
因为如之前所说
them this way what it means is that g is
not secure. Because just as we did before
容易构造一个统计测试来区分G的输出
和均匀分布的序列
it's very easy to build a statistical test
that will distinguish the output of G from
但如果G不安全，根据姚定理
uniform. So G is not secure. But if G Is not
secure, by Yao's Theorem, that means that
意味着G是可预测的，换句话说
存在某个位置I，给定输出前I位
G is predectible. So in other words, there
exists some I for which given the first I
你能预测出第I+1位，好
bits of the output, you can build
the I+1 bits of the output. Okay, so
即使我不能为大家构造预测算法
我们知道这个预测一定存在
even though I can't quite point to you a
predictor, we know that a predictor must
这就是姚定理的一个可爱的应用
exist. So that's a one cute simple
application of Yao theorem. Now before we
现在在我们结束本节前
对我们所做的进行一点推广
end the segment I want to kind of,
generalize a little bit of what we did.
引入一些将来会很有用的记号
And introduce a little bit of important
notation that's going to be useful
那么我们推广
actually throughout. So, we're gonna
generalize the concept of
与均匀分布不可区分的概念
到两个一般分布间的不可区分
indistinguishability from uniform, to
indistinguishability of two general
设想我给出分布p1和p2，我问
distributions. So, suppose I give you p1
and p2, and we ask, can these two
这两个分布可区分吗？
我们说这些分布
distributions be distinguished? And so
we'll say that the distributions are
计算上不可区分，记为p1波浪线p2
computationally indistinguishable, and
we'll denote this by p1, a squiggly p. P2.
这意味着在多项式时间里
p1无法与p2相区分
This means that, in polynomial time, P1
cannot be distinguished from P2. And we'll
我们说它们是不可区分的，与之前一样
say that they're indistinguishable,
basically, just as before
对所有有效的统计测试A
if basically for all, efficient, statistical
tests, statistical tests A, it so happens
如果我从分布p1里取样，将结果
交由A进行测试
that if I sample from the distribution P1.
And I give the output to A. Versus if I
作为对比，我从p2中取样，也交给A
sample from the distribution P2, and I
give the sample to A. Then basically A
那么基本上A对两种情况表现一致
换句话说，两概率的差别
behaves the same in both cases. In
other words, the difference between these
是可忽略的。这个对所有统计测试都成立
two probabilities is negligible. And this
has to be true for all statistical tests.
对所有统计测试，对吧？
如果是这种情况，我们说
For all efficient statistical tests. Okay?
So if this is the case then we say that,
A无法区分，它区分两分布的优势
well A couldn't distinguish. Its advantage
in distinguishing two distributions is
是可忽略的，如果这点对所有
有效的统计测试都成立
negligible and if that's true for all
efficient statistical tests then we say
我们说，这两个分布是计算上
不可区分的
that the distributions are basically
computationaly indistinguishable,
因为一个有效算法不能区分它们
because an efficient algorithm cannot
distinguish them. And just to show you how
告诉大家这个记号很有用
使用它来表述安全PRG的定义
useful this notation is, basically using
this notation the definition of security
如果我给出一个伪随机分布
for PRG just says. That if I give you a
pseudo-random distribution. In other
换句话说，我随机选取密钥K
输出相应的G
words, I choose K at random, and that
outputs a G of K. That distribution is
这个分布与均匀分布是计算上不可区分的
computationally indistinguishable from the
uniform distribution. So you can see this,
可以看到，这个非常简单的记号
抓住了伪随机数发生器的整个定义
this very simple notation captures the
whole definition of pseudo-random
好，我们后面会用到这个记号
generators. Okay, so we're gonna make use
of this notation. In the next segment,
下一节我们定义密码的安全
when we define, what does it mean for a
cipher to be secure.